so let's start with deficiency nutrients
and just to clarify when we're talking
about deficiency we're talking about not
clinical deficiency meaning you know if
someone has low enough levels of vitamin
D they have rickets or if they have low
enough levels of vitamin C they have
scurvy
but between optimum levels and a full-on
disease state is a pretty big room for
sub-optimal and so we want to talk about
what our optimal ranges for various
nutrients that are needed for not just
health in general but specifically
cognitive and psychological so if if
people are kind of new coming to this
what are the foundations of nutrition
that are relevant for brain health and
chemistry well I think it would be best
to kind of start off by clarifying you
know deficiencies and excesses some some
of the nutrients have a very narrow
spectrum of deficiency in excess so that
they're very narrowly focused into a
range of optimal but the Bruce Ames did
a really good job of talking about
micronutrients and his triage theory of
them and and I think it applies well
from what I've seen in clinical practice
where the body has has two different
mechanisms at work you have the the
everyday function the survival function
where it's using certain nutrients and
and there they're allocated to the
everyday survival but then in the
background of that we also have long
term survival and long term aspects of
like DNA repair and monitoring and
things like that but when we when we get
deficient we may not have overt signs of
deficiency because it's being triaged so
they're taking the limited amount of
nutrient that we have the body does this
and and allocates it to the things that
we need for daily survival and so we may
not be aware of this ongoing deficiency
of some micronutrients or a macro
nutrient even that could be impairing
long-term survival benefits and so you
know looking at
at it from a symptomatology standpoint
it's it's kind of it's kind of vague
when we go with symptoms so what we want
to look at is what are the items that
are are really significant that we need
to get in everyday to maintain not only
that that daily aspect but also that
long-term survival piece yep long-term
survival and optimization obviously go
together right because if we're if we
have enough calcium in the blood for all
the critical calcium ion channel stuff
that has to happen daily but we're
moving slowly into osteopenia where some
of the reserves are decreasing we're
also moving into sub optimal function
even though we're still asymptomatic
yeah and we have I mean we have systems
in place the body is capable of making
many things but we also have some
essential nutrients and then we have
what we call conditionally essential
nutrients which are nutrients that the
body can make but under under stressors
or increased demand the body can't keep
up with needs so we need to get those
into our diet in some way so do you
think amino acids are a good place to
start for brand new yeah that's a great
place to start I mean you know we we
deal with with amino acids the buddies
body's capable of making most of the
amino acids but we also have the
essential amino acids which the body
can't make you know we're there's not
we're one of the few organisms on this
planet that has two that can't make all
of the proteins that we need in our body
we we have to have certain amino acids
that are going to be able to be taken in
in the diet that we're not capable of
making but we need to survive you know
in so having a good balance of that
intake of protein is essential and
proteins have different biologic values
when it comes to the amount of essential
amino acids that are present in them we
see a lot of issues with people who have
low protein intake that are vegetarian
and so it's not that the vegetarian
aspect is in any way negative but it's
something that you want to
pay attention to because you will need
to supplement certain things to maintain
adequate nutrition especially a
cognitive function in that situation so
for the those who don't know what is the
role of amino acids in neuro chemistry
well the amino acids are the building
blocks of all proteins and there's these
proteins can take the form of of
receptors they can take the form of
neuromodulators there's they're the
building blocks of what we require in
order to function in an optimal state
and when we don't have that ability to
build those it's like having like you're
building a house and you have all of the
essential pieces to build that house but
the nails are missing so you can have
all of the additional wood and you can
have excess of bricks and everything
like that but if you're missing the
nails or the mortar then you're not
going to have a solid structure and that
goes the same with neuro chemistry if
you don't have all of these nutrients
that are there to balance out and make
everything that's needed you're gonna
you're gonna end up with deficiencies so
I think a specific simple interesting
point for people is that brain has a lot
of different kind of signaling chemicals
peptides and endorphins and neural
hormones and the neurotransmitters that
many of us are used to hearing of
dopamine and serotonin are the most
commonly heard of happiness related kind
of psychiatric hormones I mean
transmitters are both made directly from
key amino acids so tryptophan converts
into serotonin and then melatonin to
sleep and dopamine or tyrosine
I mean dopamine from tyrosine or phenyl
alanine so this means if someone is not
either getting enough dietary amino
acids so they're not getting enough
protein or they're not breaking it down
or absorbing or assimilating it they
literally don't have the building blocks
necessary for keener
Trane's hunters right and I mean you've
got to look at it from a total system
standpoint to I mean you know do they
have the the mechanisms in place to
utilize those amino acids as well so
you've got to not only have that that
precursor piece but you've got to have
the steps in between to get to that
final output and you know we've seen
some issues with that with with some of
the tyrosine hydroxylase
deficiencies where you can get adequate
amino acids but you're not actually
converting it into the dopamine right in
the end result so what are some of the
will kind of move from amino acids for a
minute what are some of the
micronutrients that are necessary to
convert amino acids and ten
neurotransmitters well and I think it's
important too to really define the
micronutrients the micronutrients are
the sort of the vitamins and minerals
that are required in and most of the
time these are required as cofactors so
they're required in those steps that I
was talking about if going from you know
the tyrosine to the dopamine you know
what are you going to need in there what
what pieces might be deficient that
could impair that v6 and is a common
micronutrient is a common deficiency
that would that we see and it can be a
rate limiting step in the creation of
neurotransmitters in the brain when we
have deficiencies vitamin D also another
one
b12 another one magnesium copper zinc I
mean these are all micronutrients that
are fairly common as far as deficiencies
are concerned in the in the American
diet I mean we talked about how balanced
are our diets are and everything but our
food chain has become very deficient in
these micronutrients and you know we do
a lot of people will say well I'm gonna
get all my micro nutrients from food and
unfortunately when you look at the micro
nutrient content of the food that we're
eating today relative to 50 years ago
there's there's significant deficiencies
in those micronutrients that we had
historically had plenty of
to watch the full episode or to
subscribe to the podcast click the link
in the description or visit us at neuro
hacker comm slash collective insights
[Music]